Eduard Mark Papers 2010.0120
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
Eduard Mark Papers
undated, 1922-2005.
2010.0120
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
15.9 Linear feet
Eduard M. Mark was a University of Connecticut educated historian who studied the Cold War era of U.S. military history. His collection consists of correspondence, notes, administrative records, transcripts, legal documents, manuscripts, photographs, news clippings, and books from the 1920s to the present.
Mark, Eduard.
Biography
Born on June 8, 1943, Eduard Mark was a historian of the Cold War, and American foreign affairs. He attended the University of Connecticut, receiving a bachelors degree in 1966 and a master's degree in 1967. After serving in the U.S. Army (1968-1970), Mark returned to the University of Connecticut, completing his doctoral work in history in 1978. The author of numerous publications, Mark was an expert on the Cold War period, and had top secret clearance to examine U.S. documents for the World War II and early post-war periods. He worked as a historian for the U.S. Department of the Air Force for most of his career, starting in 1982 and continuing until his death in 2009. Mark had completed numerous articles and books on U.S. policy towards Eastern Europe, U.S. perceptions of Stalinism, the Alger Hiss case, and the evolution of Stalin's policy toward Europe during and after World War II during his career.
General note
Published Works:
Aerial Interdiction: Airpower and the Land Battle in Three American Wars, Washington, D.C.: Center for Air Force History, 1994.
Defending the West: the United States Air Force and European Security, 1946-1998, Washington, D.C.: Air Force History and Museums Program, 1999.
Revolution by Degrees: Stalin's National-Front Strategy for Europe, 1941-1947, Washington, D.C.: Woodrow Wilson International Center for Scholars, 2001.
Scope and Content Note
The Eduard Mark Papers consists of materials used by Mark in his research as a historian of the Cold War era in U.S. history. A majority of the collection spans the years 1945-1960, with some materials falling before and after this timeline. The collection includes correspondence, notes, administrative records, transcripts, legal documents, manuscripts, photographs, clippings and books. These sources, which contain military and government correspondence, military reports, declassified documents and other materials, shed light on a myriad of topics relating to the Cold War, including military strategies and positioning, negotiations, intelligence and national security, territorial problems, military propaganda, international relations and European affairs. Not all sources in the collection are in English. Mark had a reading knowledge of German, Classical Greek and Latin, Russian, French, Bulgarian and Romanian. Some sources are in Russian.
Materials in the collection consists of government correspondence, military correspondence, declassified documents, Russian documents, film reels, and news clippings. Subjects included in the collection consist of the Soviet Union, military strategies and positioning, negotiations, the OSS, international relations, reports on resistance, military propaganda, the Chicago Daily, Eastern Europe and Soviet Communications, the National Archives, and Cabinet Distribution. Publications by Mark in the collection include, Post-Fascist Democratic Transition, Stalin terror in the Comintern: New Perspectives, The Carl Beck Papers, 'A Glooming Peace:' The General Strategy of the United States and the Defense of Western Europe, 1946-1954, and an untitled book about Romania.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated to the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center by Eduard Mark's family in 2010.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to the University, its history, administration, faculty, staff and students. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the Reading Room desk.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Mark, Eduard Maximilian.; Administrative Records.; Authors.; Correspondence.; Historians.; Manuscripts.; Notes.; Photocopies.; Photographs.; Typescripts.; United States. Air Force. History Program.
- Series I: Inventory, undated, 1922-2005
  - Correspondence, notes, administrative records, transcripts, legal documents, 1945-1947 (Box 1)
    General note
    [Subjects include: Government correspondence, war notes/strategies, military correspondence.]
  - Legal documents, notes, transcripts, manuscripts, correspondence, Bulk, 1943-1947; 1939, 1943-1947, 1996 (Box 2)
    [Subjects include: Government correspondence, War notes, Soviet Russia, Military strategies and positioning, Military correspondence.]
  - Correspondence, administrative records, 1944-1947 (Box 3)
    [Subjects include: War strategies, Federal government, correspondence, negotiations, declassified documents, OSS, International Relations, Russian documents.]
  - Administrative records, legal documents, notes, photographs, manuscripts, newspaper clippings, correspondence, 1945-1947, 1963, 1987-1996 (Box 4)
    [Subjects include: International Relations, reports on the Resistance, military propaganda, Russian documents, foreign policy.]
  - Publications, correspondence, notes, administrative records, books, manuscripts, Bulk, 1943-1958; 1922, 1934, 1943-1958, 1977 (Box 5)
    [Subjects include: Russian documents, Intelligence and National Security, Territorial Problems, European Affairs, Foreign Affairs.]
  - Correspondence, manuscripts, transcripts, newspaper clippings, administrative records, post cards, notes, publications, 1942-2005 (Box 6)
    [Subjects include: Russian documents, International Relations, Russia and Soviet Union Relations, Cryptology, National Security.]
  - Visual recordings, note cards, newspaper clippings, manuscripts, transcripts, publications, administrative records, correspondence, 1936-1990 (Box 7)
    [Subjects include: (3) Film Reels, Chicago Daily, General Comments on A American Policy, Eastern Europe and Soviet Communication.]
  - Publications, transcripts, administrative records, correspondence, 1946-1950 (Box 8)
    [Subjects include: National Archives, Foreign Relations.]
  - Transcripts, correspondence, administrative records, 1943-1947 (Box 9)
    [Subjects include: Foreign Office, Prime Minister's Personal Telegrams.]
  - Transcripts, correspondence, administrative records, 1943-1947 (Box 10)
    [Subjects include: Foreign Office, Cabinet Distribution.]
  - Manuscripts, administrative records, transcripts, 1942-1944 (Box 11)
    [Subjects include: War Cabinet, Foreign Documents.]
  - Manuscripts, Publications, 1944-1989 (Box 12)
    Scope and Contents note
    [Subjects include: Post-Fascist Democratic Transition, Stalin terror in the Comintern: New Perspectives, The Carl Beck Papers.]
  - Manuscripts, undated; 0.9 Linear feet Folders with labeled tabs (Box 2012.0075_1)
    Scope and Content Note
    Subjects include: "'A Glooming Peace:' The General Strategy of the United States and the Defense of Western Europe, 1946-1954", untitled book about Romania.